Inventory of the Walter McGowan Upchurch Papers, 1927-1988
Duke University Archives David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Walter McGowan Upchurch Papers, 1927-1988
University Archives, Duke University
Upchurch, Walter McGowan.
1.0 Linear Feet approx. 750 Items
Upchurch was a Duke University Trustee as well as the founder of the Chapel Choir.
Collection includes photographs, correspondence, and subject files.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 24-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Collection is open for research except for one file which is restricted for 50 years (noted in the container list).
Provenance
The Walter McGowan Upchurch Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1989.
Biographical Note
Walter McGowan Upchurch, Jr. was a trustee of Duke University and the founder of Duke's Chapel Choir. He was also an executive of Shell Oil. Upchurch graduated from Duke University with an A.B. in 1931 and a law degree in 1936. In 1933, he founded the Duke Chapel Choir and became its first director. He became director of Placement Services in 1940, which helped provide educational and placement help for students and alumni. Upchurch served as a Duke trustee from 1964-1977, when he was named trustee emeritus. He received the University Medal for Distinguished Meritorious Service in December 1988 and passed away in January 1989.
Collection Overview
Collection includes materials related to the Duke Chapel Choir, reunions, Shell Oil, correspondence, and photographs. Please be aware of the restricted Board of Trustees file, which is restricted for 50 years.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Duke University--History.
Duke University. Board of Trustees.
Duke University. Chapel Choir.
Related Material
Walter McGowan Upchurch Papers held in "general collections" of the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Detailed Description of Collection
- Container List, (2 boxes)
  - Photograph of Upchurch, circa 1930s (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Duke Campus, circa 1930s (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1930s-1980s (Box 1)
  - Photographs: Quadrangle Pictures, 1930s (Box 1)
  - Commencement Programs, 1934-1935 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Church: Service of Worship, 1940, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Theater Programs: Duke and Durham, 1927-1942 (Box 1)
  - Theater Programs: NYC, 1927-1928 (Box 1)
  - Theater Programs: NYC, 1932-1944 (Box 1)
  - Organ and Carillon Recital Programs, 1934-1951 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Publications, 1935-1960 (Box 1)
  - Aeolian Organ, 1932-1940, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Published Music Compositions (for choirs) (Box 1)
  - Upchurch's Collection of Sacred Music, undated (Box 1)
  - Summer School Choir, 1938-1941 (Box 1)
  - Summer School, 1940-1941 (Box 1)
  - Speech: "A Tribute to Mr. Brown - A Friend to the Young People," 1927 (Box 2)
  - Speech: Fannie Mitchell Day, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Biographical Information, 1964-1988 (Box 2)
  - Cetificates and Diplomas, 1970-1973 (Box 2)
  - Chapel Choir Reunion, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1941, 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with Duke University Archives, 1986-1988 (Box 2)
  - Duke Endowment, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Duke Law School Class of 1936, 50th Year Reunion, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Hoof 'N' Horn, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Pi Kappa Alpha: Alpha Alpha Chapter Membership Binder, 1975-1983 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippins, 1937-1988 (Box 2)
  - Quadrangle Pictures, 1934-1983 (Box 2)
  - Shell International Fellowships Program, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Shell Oil Company, 1954-1971 (Box 2)
  - Robert Durden Articles from the North Carolina Historical Review, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - RESTRICTED Board of Trustees, 1974-1988 (Box 2)